<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resource xmlns="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-4 http://schema.datacite.org/meta/kernel-4/metadata.xsd">
<identifier identifierType="DOI">https://doi.org/10.48539/HBM446.WGLG.755</identifier>
<titles>
	<title>Anatomical Structures, Cell Types, plus Biomarkers (ASCT+B) table for Placenta Full Term v1.0</title>
</titles>
<creators>
	<creator>
		<creatorName>Louise Laurent</creatorName>
		<givenName>Louise</givenName>
		<familyName>Laurent</familyName>
		<nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2095-7534">0000-0002-2095-7534</nameIdentifier>
	</creator>
	<creator>
		<creatorName>Mana Parast</creatorName>
		<givenName>Mana</givenName>
		<familyName>Parast</familyName>
		<nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/000-0001-5963-2246">000-0001-5963-2246</nameIdentifier>
	</creator>
	<creator>
		<creatorName>Kathleen Fisch</creatorName>
		<givenName>Kathleen</givenName>
		<familyName>Fisch</familyName>
		<nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0117-7444">0000-0002-0117-7444</nameIdentifier>
	</creator>
</creators>
<publisher>HuBMAP</publisher>
<publicationYear>2022</publicationYear>
<resourceType resourceTypeGeneral="Dataset">ASCT+B Table</resourceType>
<subjects>
	<subject>Placenta Full Term v1.0</subject>
</subjects>
<contributors>
	<contributor contributorType="ProjectLeader">
		<contributorName>Katy Börner</contributorName>
		<givenName>Katy</givenName>
		<familyName>Börner</familyName>
		<nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3321-6137">0000-0002-3321-6137</nameIdentifier>
	</contributor>
	<contributor contributorType="Other">
		<contributorName>Drucilla Roberts</contributorName>
		<givenName>Drucilla</givenName>
		<familyName>Roberts</familyName>
		<nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9104-6674">0000-0002-9104-6674</nameIdentifier>
	</contributor>
</contributors>
<dates>
	<date dateType="Available">2022-05-06</date>
</dates>
<descriptions>
	<description>Anatomical Structures, Cell Types, plus Biomarkers (ASCT+B) tables aim to capture the nested part_of structure of anatomical human body parts, the typology of cells, and biomarkers used to identify cell types. The tables are authored and reviewed by an international team of experts. The Placenta ASCT+B table represents terms related to the full term human placenta. These include both macroscopic and microscopic anatomical structures, major cell types, and protein and lipid biomarkers specific for each cell type listed. This table was generated based on published placental histopathologic nomenclature, as well as published literature on cell-type specific biomarkers. Most of the markers listed are observed in more than 1 study or orthogonally validated. Note that these are predicted markers and a single marker to annotate a cell type is not likely sufficient or specific. Where more refined cell types are not available in the ontologies, the closest general term is used. For example, there are likely multiple types of placental stromal cells; however, further characterization is needed to distinguish between these cell types. Where cells of similar type occur in different locations, the closest and highest level of resolution available is used. For example, vascular endothelial cells (CL0000071) occur in multiple different contexts within the placenta, including the umbilical vessels, chorionic plate vessels, chorionic stem villous vessels and capillaries, and decidual vessels; similarly, vascular smooth muscle cells (CL0000359) occur in umbilical vessels, chorionic plate vessels, and chorionic stem villous vessels.  These markers may not cover early term placentas or placentas from more complicated pregnancies. Since these are just a guide, more accurate annotation should be done using the entire set of enriched genes in a cluster and using placentas of varying gestational ages and pregnancies. The cell types shown here are at much higher granularity, although general markers for many of the structures are also shown. There is a tradeoff in uncertainty of cell type annotation with higher granularity and as spatial validation approaches become more robust we will be accordingly revising these.</description>
</descriptions>
<language>EN</language>
<alternateIdentifiers>
	<alternateIdentifier alternateIdentifierType="HuBMAP ID">HBM446.WGLG.755</alternateIdentifier>
	<alternateIdentifier alternateIdentifierType="How to Cite This Data Table">Louise Laurent; Mana Parast; Kathleen Fisch, HuBMAP ASCT+B Tables. Placenta Full Term v1.0. https://doi.org/10.48539/HBM446.WGLG.755</alternateIdentifier>
	<alternateIdentifier alternateIdentifierType="How to Cite ASCT+B Tables Overall">Quardokus, Ellen, Bruce W. Herr II, Lisel Record,  Katy Börner. 2022. [*HuBMAP ASCT+B Tables*.]( https://hubmapconsortium.github.io/ccf/pages/ccf-anatomical-structures.html) Accessed on May 6, 2022</alternateIdentifier>
</alternateIdentifiers>
<formats>
	<format>.csv</format>
</formats>
<rightsList>
	<rights rightsURI="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</rights>
</rightsList>
<fundingReferences>
	<fundingReference>
		<funderName>National Institutes of Health</funderName>
		<awardNumber>OT2OD026671</awardNumber>
	</fundingReference>
</fundingReferences>
</resource>
